Guide to the Morris Hillquit Papers TAM.027
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Morris Hillquit Papers
1906-1959
TAM.027
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
Morris Hillquit (1896-1933) was a socialist candidate, leader, lawyer, author and prominent theoretician of the Socialist Pary. The papers contain correspondence, including letters by James Oneal, August Claessens and Julius Gerber; manuscripts; campaign literature; printed ephemera; clippings, photographs and other papers, including the text of a debate with Bertrand Russell, and the typescript of "Builders of World Socialism," (1962) an unpublished book by Hillquit's daughter, Nina.
Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933
Box 1-2
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
The Papers are organized into one alphabetically arranged series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Morris Hillquit (1896-1933) was a socialist leader, lawyer, author and prominent theoretician of the Socialist Pary. He ran twice for mayor of New York City and five times for the House of Representatives, always unsuccessfully.
Provenance
Gift of Nina Hillquit (daughter), 1957.
Scope and Contents note
The papers contain correspondence; manuscripts of addresses, particularly relating to Hillquit's political campaigns; campaign literature; printed ephemera; clippings, photographs and other papers. Also included are letters by James Oneal discussing Hillquit's representation of United States oil companies in a suit with the USSR; correspondence with August Claessens and Julius Gerber; the manuscript of "Builders of World Socialism," and a typescript of "Builders of World Socialism," (1962) an unpublished book by Hillquit's daughter, Nina; an address (1912) at a local New York socialist meeting, and the text of a debate with Bertrand Russell, "Is the British Labor Government Revolutionary?"
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives and elsewhere
At the Wisconsin Historical Society (Madison, WI) are the Morris Hillquit Papers, 1895-1943. 3.2 cubic feet (10 reels of microfilm), and Photographs. Online finding aid available at:
http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=wiarchives;cc=wiarchives;q1=hillquit;rgn=main;view=text;didno=uw-whs-ny00h
Claessens, August, 1885-1954 -- |v Correspondence; Gerber, Julius, 1862-1916 -- |v Correspondence; Haywood, Big Bill, 1869-1928.; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933; Hillquit, Nina; Oneal, James, b. 1875.; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970; Socialist Party (U.S.).; Black-and-white photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Socialism |z United States.; Socialists |z United States.; Women socialists |z United States.
- Papers
  - Biographical: Memorabilia, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical: "Morris Hillquit: American Social Democrat" by Robert William Iversen, Jan 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical: "Morris Hillquit: An Address" by Alexander Kahn, Jun 24, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brandeis University, 1957, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings: Biographical, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: Debates, May 5, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: General, 1912-1933, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings: S.S. Hillquit (Liberty Ship), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Belgian Labor Party, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Claessens, August, 1915, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: General, 1928, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Gerber, Julius, May 8, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Holiday Cards (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Lee, Algernon, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: National Civic Federation, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Rand School, Nov 4, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: 60th Birthday, Oct 18, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Soviet Oil Case, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Death and Commemeration, 1933, 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Debate: "Is the British Government Revolutionary?" (Affirmative: Hillquit, Morris; Negative: Bertrand, Russell. Carnegie Hall. Typescript, 60 Pages), May 5, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Debate: "What Shall the Attitude of the Socialist Party Be Toward the Economic Organization of the Workers?" (Hillquit, Morris versus Haywood, William. Cooper Union. Typescript, 70 Pages), Jan 11, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Elections: Hillquit, Morris, 1906-1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Writings, Published, Leaflets and Brief Pamphlets, 1908-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Writings, Published, "The Red Flag and the Stars and Stripes" (New York Call), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Writings, Published, The Workers' Rights Amendment (H.J. Res 327), Jun 17, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Writings, Unpublished, "Comrade Bull Moose" (Typescript, 6 Pages), 1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hillquit, Morris: Writings, Unpublished, "The Socialist Party" (Typescript, 8 Pages), 1907 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Correspondence, 1944-1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 1-67a), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 68-132), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 133-205), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 206-302), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 303-349), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hillquit, Nina: Writings, Unpublished, "Builders of World Socialism" (Typescript, pages 350-415), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (Almost All of Morris Hillquit Only), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trachtenberg, Alexander: "American Socialism and the War" (Publisher's Proof; Introduction by Hillquit, Morris), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals: Clippings, Biographical (Restricted), 1931-1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Fragile Originals: Clippings: Brandeis, Debates, General (Restricted), 1912-1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fragile Originals: Soviet Oil Case (Restricted), 1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fragile Originals: Writings, Published, Brief Pamphlet (Restricted), May 11, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 9)